Previously on "The 100"...
The valley is ours.
As long as you stay here,
we won't have a problem.
The hydrofarm is barely feeding us now.
So if this is the last
living valley on the Earth,
then it should be ours.
Diyoza thinks the same thing.
And so we fight.
Oh, my God, they're breeding them.
You're gonna suck today.
No one can think that you'd
make a good Commander.
- Yaah! uh!
- Yaah!
Madi, I could really use a second.
What do you say?
I have a question for Colonel Diyoza.
What would it take for
you to share the valley?
Short of an unconditional surrender.
- Nothing.
- Octavia will never surrender.
That's why we're gonna take her out.
I don't care how you
make it happen, Clarke.
Kill Octavia is you have to.
Bring her to me in chains,
and I'll do it for you,
or she can surrender herself,
but your red queen doesn't
seem like the type.
Let us worry about that.
We have an understanding, then.
- We do.
- Good.
Call me back when it's done,
and we can work out the
details of your crossing.
Over and out.
- No way.
- Bellamy...
We are not killing my sister, Clarke.
I don't care how crazy she is.
Run the loop. The rover's charged.
We're getting our friends.
That was reckless.
We had a plan. You agreed.
That was before Octavia
made Madi her second.
That army marches to war
as soon as they find
out the eye is down.
- I can't let that happen.
- So we don't tell anyone?
They'll know as soon as we drive away.
Oh, who cares? We grab Madi, and we go.
Bellamy, she's by her side.
- She's my sister, Clarke.
- I know.
Tell me what else to do.
- We stop the war.
- How?
- Algae.
- Monty...
Cooper already gave me
permission to show what it can do.
She's meeting me before
the afternoon meal
- so I can take her to the...
- That's enough.
- Hey, give it back.
- Monty, Bellamy's right.
Cooper's worse than Octavia.
No offense.
Besides, the first batch put Murphy
in a coma for almost a week.
- By the time it's ready to eat...
- The first culture,
and we're not gonna eat it this time.
We're gonna feed it to the plants.
If I can make the farm viable again,
then we'll still have a chance.
The spy did her job?
Uh, we were just about to send for you.
Told you Echo would get it done.
Can the enemy still see us?
For now, yes. It's technical, but...
He has to run a loop to
mask our troop movements.
When the time comes, we
need to clear the surface
to reduce the risk of anyone noticing
the same people moving in
the same direction again and again.
Well done, Monty.
Load the worms into the rover
and mobilize the army.
War is here.
- Synced and corrected by medvidecek007 -
- www.addic7ed.com -
He's all yours, Colonel.
Thank you, Robert.
Going somewhere, Kane?
Do I need permission for that?
- Yes.
- Ok.
I was going to the Southwest quadrant
to map out a settlement.
Just breathe, Robert.
It's ok.
Comes and goes. I'll be fine.
Damn right you will.
New Doc's working on a cure.
Why not give him something for the pain?
Meanwhile, why don't
you get off your feet?
You look like hell.
Thank you, Colonel.
List of the people you killed?
For that, I need a bigger notebook.
Why am I here, Colonel?
I got an interesting
call on the radio...
Abby's daughter.
Clarke radioed?
Why?
I think she may try and
kill your red queen.
She'll get killed.
Maybe, but I told her once it's done
and Wonkru surrenders...
Do you read me?
We'll share this valley.
Testing, testing for the 200th time.
This is John Murphy.
That's John Murphy.
- Let me talk to him.
- Just wait.
Testing, testing.
This is John Murphy looking
for Colonel Diyoza.
Do you read me?
Well, it's safe to say you're better
at blowing things up than fixing them.
This is Colonel Diyoza.
What do you want?
Be strong, direct, unrelenting.
We have McCreary.
You ever want to see him alive again,
you give us Raven Reyes.
You know him.
Will he follow through?
Probably.
Colonel, if you don't make the trade,
- McCreary's people...
- Become my people.
You should have learned the last time
you held my people hostage
that I don't negotiate with terrorists.
That's funny coming from you.
Last chance, our hostage for yours.
May God have mercy on his soul.
Two radio calls, two problems solved.
What are the odds?
That could've gone better.
Call me when he's awake.
I need some air.
Come on, Kane.
Without graveyard McCreary,
my internal problem is solved.
Without the Red Queen,
our problem external is.
This is how we get to peace.
Is it? Because from where I'm standing,
it looks like we're trading
one dictator for another...
Political assassinations, torture,
wrongful imprisonment.
This is about me giving Abby pills.
You mean, feeding an addict's addiction
to save your people's lives
without a thought for the
life you're destroying?
Yes. It is.
I've seen the horrors
we inflict on each other
in the name of survival, Colonel.
God knows I'm as guilty as anyone,
but we're on the brink here,
on the edge of an abyss I've stared
into before, and I can tell you,
having sacrificed the few to save
the many more times
than I care to admit,
eventually, the few becomes the many.
The ends don't always justify the means,
and if you don't know that by now
after everything you've been through...
Then you're just as bad as Octavia...
And we're already lost.
That's a fair amount of
abscesses, isn't it, Doctor?
Wait.
- Did you feel that?
- Feel what?
One of the abscesses broke apart.
It was the sound waves.
I'm sure of it.
I can dissolve them
and then suction out the residue. Huh.
I just need more power.
Vinson, where are you going?
Inspiration loves company.
- I'll take that if you don't mind.
- Hey, man.
A sonic drill.
It uses sound waves to pulverize rock.
That's a good idea, Vinson,
but unless there's a
prisoner at this camp
that's an engineer, there's...
Yaagh! Please...
Turn it up a little bit.
Eegh! Ugh! Uh!
Raven, no. It's not your fight.
It's our fault he's here.
I know you're angry,
but you said yourself
they can't kill him.
He's the only person who...
We have to kill him.
No way.
Raven, that ship is their
biggest strategic advantage.
Without a pilot to fly...
I said no.
- Listen to me.
- There's nothing you have to say
- that I could possibly...
- My friend Echo wants to kill you
so they have no one to fly the ship.
If you tell Diyoza, I'll deny it.
We're readying for war.
Do you know the risk I'm
taking meeting you here?
- Yes. Thank you for coming.
- What do you want?
I talked to Colonel Diyoza.
She's offering all of Wonkru
safe passage to the valley.
All Octavia has to do is surrender.
As it's by now you've realized
she would never do that,
I'll ask you again.
What do you want from me?
Peace without war is still possible.
Now, you're her advisor.
She'll listen to you.
Why would I advise her to surrender
in a war she's likely to win?
Thanks to you, we can march freely
on the enemy while the
worms ravage them.
By the time we get to the valley,
the only thing left to do
will be to clean up the mess.
And if the worms ravage the valley?
A risk she's willing to take.
- Are you?
- It's not up to me.
- What if it was?
- Clarke...
I will not help you kill my leader.
Neither will I.
What if the outcome of
the war wasn't certain,
if she didn't have the worms?
Would she still fight?
If she didn't have the worms,
- both sides would take heavy losses.
- Exactly.
If all it took to save
her people from that
and deliver them to the promised land
was surrender, would she do it?
I would hope so.
Of course, you would never
see the promised land
because she would know it was you
and, brother or not,
throw you in the pits.
Not if she thought it was Cooper.
There's a failsafe in
the processing room...
I saw it when I was there...
A way to kill the worms if they ever...
Folly! Cooper would
never push that button,
and since she's the only one
that handles the worms...
Cooper would be dead.
We'll make it look like an accident.
You would be the first responder.
You would hit the failsafe button.
No more worms.
No more war.
We know that there are
3 entry points to the valley.
While Cooper, Madi, and
I soften the battlefield,
Miller will lead the first battalion
through the Southern tributary.
- First?
- You have a problem with that?
No, but the first battalion's Indra's.
Not anymore.
It's fine, Nathan. You're prepared.
All right. Madi, come here by me.
Cooper, the floor is yours.
Worms are thermoreceptors.
That means they sense body heat.
With Madi's knowledge of the woods,
we'll get as close to
the village as we can
and release them here, here,
and here.
Which one of you is Raven Reyes?
Why is he wearing a collar?
- You don't want to know.
- Tell me.
Serial killer.
He kept his victims' hands
and feet as mementos.
Other than that, he's a nice guy.
Hmm.
What's this about, Vinson?
Collar looks good on you, Shaw.
Yours has been tagged to
another facility for the day.
Now walk with me.
I'll be ok.
- Good.
- Hey, man.
Abby. Oh...
Thank you, Vinson.
I've been here for days.
You're not collared.
I saw Kane. Why haven't I seen you?
I'm sorry.
Echo said you defected
because of Octavia.
Did they tell you why you are here?
No.
The miners are sick.
I know. The hythylodium.
Listen. I think I can cure them.
I need you to be able to
take the power from this
and make it come out of this.
No. If they're dying, let them.
Raven, I'm a doctor. I cannot do that.
Now please just tell me if
it's even at all possible.
Sure. It's possible,
but I'm not doing it.
Raven, please.
I need this to work.
Abby, what aren't you telling me?
Did Diyoza threaten to hurt you?
I don't like it, but
I'll see what I can do.
I admit it.
I'm impressed.
Your mother would be proud, Monty.
I told you.
It's the nitrogen,
and that took less than a day.
In a week, the entire farm could be...
You don't want to do that.
The first culture,
even from an old strain
like this, isn't safe.
I mean, it is for the plants,
but on the ring,
it put one of my friends in a coma.
I'll keep that in mind.
Monty, here's the truth.
We leave in a few hours.
After that, I don't ever want
to see this place again.
If you want to take it over,
be my guest.
If you'll excuse me...
You don't have to leave.
Look. That's the point.
No one else has to die.
You did things to survive.
That's in the past.
We can have protein
and biofuel and beer.
Yeah. It tastes like crap,
but who cares if it gets you drunk?
Is someone there?
Mm! Uh!
Bellamy!
Monty, come on.
We need you to open the processing room.
What the hell are you doing?
Explain later.
Actually, if you want
me to open that door,
you'll explain now.
I know it doesn't look like it,
but this is how we stop the war.
I was stopping the war.
Keep your voice down.
If anyone hears us...
You're killing her, aren't you?
Yes.
If you don't open that door,
we're the ones who get killed.
Open it, Monty.
And, of course, I help
because what's one more, right?
- We're already murders.
- That's not fair.
We're talking about taking
one life to save hundreds.
Really? Then let's kill Octavia.
Didn't think so.
Monty...
We're doing the right thing.
If you say it enough,
maybe I'll believe you.
Looks like I should have killed you
when I had the chance.
Yeah? Well, I'm hard to kill.
Emori, he's up.
Getting blown up must suck, huh?
No. Chronic lung disease is worse.
I'll take your word for it.
Emori!
The bomb was clever, though.
Yeah. It was. Rocket fuel.
You should see what hythylodium does
when it's weaponized.
I could use someone like you on my crew.
Now, see, that's funny to me
because your crew doesn't seem
to miss you much at all.
We offered to trade you for Raven,
yet here you still are.
Diyoza said no.
Well, actually, I believe
her exact words were,
"may God have mercy on his soul."
I can help you
get Raven back.
I'm listening.
Thanks, Cash. Wait here.
I've been fighting the abuse of power
my whole life, Kane.
I'm no dictator.
I want to see an end to the violence
just as badly as you.
Yet those weren't exactly
civil engineering plans
I saw in your notebook, were they?
Page after page of battle strategies.
Defense strategies.
I'm not preparing for war.
I'm planning for peace.
There's a difference.
Maybe so, but until you recognize
that we're all just people,
all this will ever be is a battlefield.
Kane, wait.
Tell me what we're looking at.
I don't think we'd see it the same way,
but all right.
That's where the trading post'll be,
and next to it, there'll be a farm
and a workshop
and a mill...
And a real medical center for Abby.
To the south, there'll be homes
dug out of the ground
to preserve the trees,
and at the center, there'll be a well,
place for people to gather, talk,
debate ideas.
And a school with a playground
where kids can blow off steam
and bitch about their teachers
and kiss under the bleachers.
My kid.
How far along?
A hundred years and 5 months,
give or take.
Abby says she's healthy.
A girl?
Was that a kick?
Thank you, Kane.
For what?
Until I met you, the thought
of raising a child in
a world like this...
You give me hope.
Hope.
That's a good name.
It is, isn't it?
Hope.
What?
Oh, no. No. No. No.
You'll both die for this.
Oh! Nngh!
Uh! No! Uh uh!
Rrgh! Aah!
Please make it stop. Aah!
Aah!
Let's go. It'll work.
Octavia will have to surrender.
Please make it stop!
This is how we get to peace.
Aagh! Why?
Aah!
Drop the gun.
- I said, drop your weapon.
- Oh, oh, hey, easy, easy, easy.
It's not loaded.
Why don't you take a minute
to explain our arrangement?
Emori.
Tell me you didn't make
a deal with the man
who tortured you and
hunted you like an animal.
- I did.
- John!
This is how we save Raven.
How?
Walk right in the front
door as his prisoners.
They'll collar us to make it
look real, but I figure...
I know how to take them off.
Mm-hmm.
Hmm, I don't know.
- We killed two of his people.
- Look, Emori.
I don't trust the guy, either,
but we want the same thing.
- What?
- To survive.
Come on. We zip in, we
get Raven, we zip out.
We get the others after, ok?
Ok. I'm in.
Good.
That's all I'm in for, John.
Look. I hate to do
this with a psychopath
sitting on the next tree,
but I thought this
- is what you wanted,
- Yes.
- you and me together
- It is.
- Working as a team.
- John, seeing you like this,
seeing you fighting to survive,
this is the John Murphy
I fell in love with.
We're running through
the woods with a killer
about to become prisoners in order
to save our friends, and I find myself
wanting to rip your clothes off.
This...
As soon as this fight is over,
you will fall apart again.
- Emori...
- No.
Trouble in paradise?
No. We're good here.
Tie her up.
All right, Abby. Fire it up.
Abby?
Come on, sleeping beauty.
You got to see this.
Abby.
What the hell, Abby?
What are you taking?
Ohh...
Raven, I can explain.
Do you remember the pain
after the City of Light?
Don't you talk to me about pain.
How does this work, you help Diyoza,
and she gives you these?
You weren't scared she
was gonna hurt you.
You were scared she was
gonna cut you off.
Raven, I will stop.
Said by every addict ever!
Well, screw that.
I will not help you get your next fix.
I didn't build this for a junkie.
Aagh!
Uh! aah!
Sorry, Raven.
Aah! D'aagh!
I am so, so sorry.
There you are.
You ok?
We were happy once, weren't we?
Yeah.
We'll get back there, I promise.
I don't want to be a killer anymore.
I don't want to take lives to save them.
Then don't.
What if I say no
and people we care about die?
They might,
but everyone dies, Monty.
Let's show them how to live.
Will you still love me
if I'm just a farmer?
When the army marches, we stay here.
I heard screams, but I was too late.
There's a hole in her glove.
Must have got in while
she was loading them up.
I'm sorry, Blodreina.
If I didn't use the gas and
the worms escaped into the bunker...
You made the right call, Indra.
Octavia, I know this isn't a good time,
but I feel it's my duty to point out
that without the worms to
soften the battlefield,
the cost in lives will be too high.
This is not a war we should fight.
Hmm, thank you for your advice, Seda,
but we weren't planning
on using the worms.
We are using their eggs.
Whoever wanted to make
this look like an accident,
they didn't know that, either.
Find Clarke and Bellamy.
You're a good brother, Bellamy.
I'm sorry that I thought I could...
Kill my sister?
The truth is,
if she was anybody else,
I would've beat you to it.
I don't know about that.
Maybe the old Bellamy, but not this one.
Suddenly, I'm the one letting
my heart rule my head.
Mama bears don't think.
They just protect their young.
Uh!
Whoa.
- Octavia...
- Take her.
You're under arrest for the
murder of Kara Cooper.
What? No. This is insane.
Is it? We weren't taking the worms.
The eggs are already
loaded in the rover,
so what was Cooper doing there?
Careful, big brother,
or I'll think you helped
her, and we don't have
enough prisoners to
settle this in the arena.
Oh, well. I guess we'll have
to settle for an execution.
- Uh...
- Let's go.
Keep Madi safe. Promise me. Uh!
I promise.
What happened to her?
You'll be happy to know
I didn't kill your pilot.
We can't let Diyoza win.
What are you saying?
Promise me he won't suffer.
Hey, did he hurt you?
I'll be right over there if you need me.
- Tell me the truth.
- Why do you care?
You're the reason these people
are still alive, right?
Their sins are on you now.
Have you ever loved someone so much
that, no matter what they do to you
or themselves,
you take it?
Mom or Dad?
Mom.
Drank herself to death.
The answer is yes.
Is it permanent?
There's still some
residual tissue damage.
You won't be running any marathons,
but I can safely say that lung disease
is not what's gonna kill you.
Well done, Abby.
How soon can you do the others?
Colonel, we got company,
movement in the east woods.
Uh, scratch that. It's McCreary.
Looks like he's got prisoners.
Everything ok?
Yes...
But it's a pity you haven't
found the cure yet.
Ruthless.
I like it.
You want your pills,
you'll keep it to yourself for now.
Do we understand each other?
Thank you for saving my life.
Hey, hey, it's McCreary.
_
Omon gon oson.
What about the girl... Madi?
She comes with us in
the rover as planned.
Omon gon oson.
Once she finds out about
it, the war will be over,
and we'll deal with it then.
Sorry, Blodreina.
Let him in.
Get some sleep. Tomorrow we ride.
So much for the 100.
- What?
- Let it go, Miller.
Don't threaten my people, Bellamy.
I can't let you kill Clarke, O.
Here we go again,
pleading for the life of a traitor
who you love.
Mom and I used to share
our rations with you.
You mind?
Only if you say the words.
Through the teeth and over the gums...
Not those words.
Omon gon oson. Say it.
Omon gon oson.
It's late, Bellamy.
If you've come here to beg, just do it.
I'm not here to beg.
I came here to tell you that I love you
very much,
no matter what happens.
I hope you believe me.
Get to the point.
I made a deal with Diyoza.
If Wonkru surrenders,
we can all live in the valley.
How...
Something's wrong.
I... I can't breathe.
Help me. Help me.
What did you do?
I dosed the bar
with Monty's algae.
I switched it with the
one we were sharing.
- Guard!
- Hey...
Hey...
Shh. You'll be ok.
By the time you wake up,
we'll be in the valley.
We will have peace.
My sister,
my responsibility.
- Synced and corrected by medvidecek007 -
- www.addic7ed.com -